All right, so most
people say they don't
want to write scripts
because it takes too
long or it makes
them sound too rigid
or they believe that,
oh, it just doesn't
make me fan as
authentic without one. But
let me tell you
about one of the
most powerful lessons that's
going to prove all
of that wrong that
I had in March
2025, about four months
before filming this. So
I started rebuilding this
course because RevTrack had
showed me all these
insights and then the
old one was now
outdated and there was
a much better way
for businesses to do
YouTube. So I spent
months planning everything, new
frameworks, examples, stories, and
to speed things up,
I thought, I'm not
going to script it
this time. I'm just
going to work from
bullet points and I'm
going to present really
naturally from them, from
like a slide deck.
And after a week
of filming, I sent
all the videos to
the editor and they
came back and they
sucked. They were confusing.
They were repetitive. They
were hard to follow.
I had to concentrate
myself just to try
and hold on to
what I was saying.
And if I am
struggling to watch it,
imagine what it's like
to watch it. I'm
not going to do
it. I'm not going
to do it. I'm
not going to do
it. I'm not going
to do it. I'm
not going to do
it. I'm not going
to do it. I'm
not going to do
it. It's going to
be like for you.
The presentation was worse.
It felt like someone
was winging it, not
someone really confidently guiding
you through a proven
system. So I scrapped
the whole thing. I
wasted thousands in production,
a week of filming,
months of work. And
even though I had
known for years that
writing was the most
important part, it just
cemented what I already
knew. Writing is what
turns your plan into
something where every single
word counts. It helps
you avoid ramble. It
allows you to hit
the points that matter.
And then when you
present it, your performance
improves and your editing
becomes 10 times faster
too, as you're not
cutting out a ton
of nonsense that's not
needed. The result of
all of this is
the same content and
the same ideas will
slip into your viewer's
brain and change their
lives rather than have
them trying to keep
up with you. Writing
takes that plan and
optimizes it for easy
understanding. Waffling points will
just never do it.
And people tell themselves
it will because they're
lazy. There's no other
reason. And I'll defend
that. They think it's
going to be faster.
And people are convinced
that it's going to
be faster. And people
are convinced that it's
going to be faster.
And people are convinced
that it's going to
be faster. And I
know that's not true.
So I'm going to
give you two of
the most powerful writing
tools in the world
that are going to
keep your viewers hooked,
as well as give
you some writing tips
that's going to make
this faster through practice
and easier. And at
the end, I'll give
you a writing system
that uses AI to
speed things up too,
without you hating the
process. So to start,
I'm going to walk
you through two of
the most powerful writing
techniques in the world
that you're going to
have to fail as
fast as you can
to master. And to
explain, I need you
to answer this. Why
a joke? Why a
joke? Why a joke?
funny? Well, it's because
when someone sets up
a joke like this,
why don't skeletons fight
each other? That raises
tension because you want
to know the answer
to it. But if
I said the punch
line first, because they
don't have the guts,
and then I set
up the start of
the joke, all of
that tension is gone
and the joke is
ruined. This is exactly
the same of YouTube
content. If you give
away the point too
early, there's no tension
that remains. Nothing the
viewer is still curious
to know. So they
stop paying attention or
comment, get to the
point. So to avoid
this, what you need
to do is think
of your video like
this graph where the
left is tension, the
viewer feels, and the
right is the length
of your video. The
intro has a setup
that creates curiosity because
it tells the viewers
what to expect and
that raises tension. And
then the points pay
off this tension one
by one, satisfying that
curiosity. But also every
intro, every transition needs
a setup that makes
viewers want to know.
So they can't know
what's coming next without
paying that off too
early. So to give
you an example of
an early payoff, this
is what it will
look like. All right,
so let's move on
to step one, which
is making sure you
don't eat yellow snow.
When you make the
point before you explain
it, viewers stop listening
because, well, remember this
image? Our brain looks
for patterns and fills
in the blanks. So
they're just going to
think, okay, I know
why I shouldn't eat
yellow snow now, and
then move on. So
instead, you do this.
All right, so let's
move on to step
one. So this mistake
put over a thousand
people in hospital last
year. I was one
of them, so let
me show you how
to avoid it. Then
you tell the story
to completion. Then you
pay off the ending,
and then you transition
into the logic brick
by setting up the
value and the reason
why they need to
listen to the logic
brick. And then you
pay off the steps
to get the result,
always keeping in mind
that we need to
keep tension high and
the viewers wanting to
know something so they
don't leave or get
bored. Without scripting, how
the hell are you
going to do that?
And when you pay
things off early, you
will see your retention
drafts dip a ton
too. So now I'm
going to show you
some very basics of
setups and payoffs. There's
some other things going
on in this script
I don't want to
focus on, but it's
just two particular areas.
So what we're going
to do is we're
going to look here.
We're going to say,
this is the transition.
So a transition hooks
forward to the next
step and sets up
some value to follow.
So it says, which
brings us on to
step four, which is
the solution to a
huge problem we all
face.
That's it, right? That's
not a very good
transition because it's not
a good transition. Because
that should have been
more specific. Something like,
brings us on to
step four, which is
going to enable you
to make videos in
two hours, not three
days. Like specifics always
better, but ignore that
for now. So YouTube
and the internet have
been around forever. And
because of that, the
chances are your viewers
have already heard the
same tips a thousand
times. So if you
give them things they
already know, it wrecks
your referral network system
as they get bored
and leave. But how
can you possibly know
what viewers already know
to get around this?
So that is a
setup because what we've
done is we've set
up a question. We've
raised curiosity, but also
that is a setup.
And what we've done
here is we've promised
some value, which also
raised curiosity. So in
this case, the payoff
of the first setup
was here.
I literally say, look,
there's a huge solution
to a problem. And
I say, the problem
is if you give
them things they know
it wrecks your referral
network system. Now I
could have done this
in multiple ways, but
I just want to
show you that. Yeah.
A setup and pay
off. Pay off can
happen within lines of
each other, but also
as you're about to
see in a second,
it could take longer.
The key thing is
as soon as you
pay off something, you
set it up.
So if we look
at this now, but
how can you possibly
know what viewers already
know to get around
this? New question, raise
curiosity. And now I
bring in the example.
Well, you can't, but
that doesn't matter if
you do what I
did in this example,
you can see on
screen right now. So
here I'm using a
visual demo and a
breakdown to simplify. So
here I'm using a
visual demo and a
breakdown to simplify. So
here I'm using a
visual demo and a
breakdown to simplify. So
you've probably watched videos
where someone says you
need to increase your
sales page conversions. And
it's like, duh, everyone
knows that's not useful.
So in this video,
instead of just repeating
the obvious, what I
did was create a
spreadsheet tool where I
loaded in the amount
of views a channel
had, and then showed
the viewers how many
sales they could expect
based on different conversion
rates of their sales
page. So this is
complex, right? So I'm
showing this in action.
I'm giving a visual
demo. What that meant
was viewers could now
see the problem for
themselves in a unique
way that made the
information feel new. I
also told viewers they
could access the information
in a different way.
I also told viewers
they could access the
information in a different
way. So I'm showing
this in action. So
the secret to driving
people from one video
to the next and
creating the referral network
is making your information
feel new. So even
if people haven't heard
it before, they remain
hooked. So what we've
got is we've got
the setup. Then the
visual demo kind of
slowly pays it off.
So the viewers are
like, I get it.
And then we just
give a final payoff
with a lesson that
cements what they thought
to be true. And
then what happens is
the payoff is done.
And then what happens
is the payoff is
done. So the curiosity
is gone. The tension
has dropped. So we
hit them with another
setup. But you don't
have to build a
spreadsheet like I did.
Making information new can
feel much simpler. So
really, all you need
to know is if
I had started this
script with, which brings
us on to step
four, which is the
solution to a huge
problem we all face.
And then if I'd
said, and that is
the secret to driving
people from one video
to the next and
creating the referral network
is making information feel
new. So even if
people haven't heard it
before, they remain hooked.
And then I gave
this visual demo. Firstly,
this might not mean
anything to them because
they can't really understand
the information within it.
But secondly, if they
do, they don't need
this, but they also
won't get the deeper
understanding or the emotional
connection or the feeling
of new, easy and
inspiring because that's what
the emotion brick an
example does. So you
have to avoid saying
step one is, and
then just giving them
the whole lesson and
then explaining. It's show
them. It's show them.
It's show them. It's
show them. Now, this
is very hard to
do. It's gonna be
one of those things
that makes writing very
overwhelming for you. You're
gonna be second guessing,
thinking how I paid
things off. Don't worry.
Nobody dies if you
pay something off early,
although I did write
a script with an
early payoff the day
before Hulk Hogan and
Ozzy Osbourne died. So
I might have to
be a bit more
vigilant in my next
script. Now, there's one
more mistake you need
to watch out for
when you're writing your
scripts. We've set up
some payoffs and to
show you what it
is, I'm gonna tell
you a joke. So
a man walks into
a doctor's and says,
Doctor, I can't see
carrots. All right. So
now let's give him
a little bit of
a warning. move on
to the next part
of writing, which is
going to get you
smashing out these scripts
really fast. Wait, wait,
wait, wait, wait, wait.
Hang on a sec.
What just happened there?
You're probably thinking, Ed,
what happened to the
rest of the joke?
Why can't he see?
And that is because
I didn't pay off
what I set up.
It's annoying, right? It's
weird. It's confusing. So
when you're writing a
script, you always need
to make sure you
pay off what you
set up in the
intro or in the
transitions. Otherwise, you're going
to frustrate the heck
out of the viewers.
Now, the AI is
going to help you
with this when you
ask it for feedback.
So don't worry too
much. But just keep
in mind, a final
check you should always
be doing is, did
I pay off everything
I set up so
that viewers don't leave
you hate? Okay, so
now we're going to
look at how to
make script writing a
bit easier because you
are going to be
in your head so
much when you do
this. And really, we
need to get you
moving fast and solve
that. So here's what
I do to avoid
that. The first thing
you want to do
is you open your
plan that you've spent
time preparing. And your
only goal is to
get to the end
of the first draft
as fast as you
can using it. So
I will write my
script. I just dump
everything out. There's no
editing. I'm not worrying
about perfect. I'm not
even worrying if it
makes that much sense
yet. I am just
trying to fill in
the blanks in the
plan and think as
little as possible. So
a first draft might
take me a couple
of hours. It could
take me four. It
might take me half
an hour. The key
here is don't rush.
But once it's written
down, your brain's going
to calm down a
lot and you'll be
able to see the
shape of your message.
Then what I do
is I present it
out loud section by
section and I end
it up with a
line. And I'm going
to edit it. And
all I'm looking for
when I'm editing is
one, is this confusing?
Two, does it make
sense? Three, could I
say the same thing
in less words? Four,
do I even need
that line? So a
great test when editing
a script is if
you can delete a
line from the script
and it works just
as well without it,
you don't need it.
So on average, I'm
going to spend two
to 10 hours editing
a script depending on
how complex it is
and how long it
was to explain. If
it's a format I'm
repeating, this can be
so much faster. Now,
you need to spend
the time here because
the results are in
the edit. So that's
the first thing I'm
going to do. And
then I'm going to
the system I use
a lot, but there
are other ways that
might suit you. So
the next way that
you can write a
script uses AI and
something called point bot.
So what you need
to do is you
want to get your
first draft down out
of your head. Now,
some people will look
at the plan and
they will record the
audio. They will then
transcribe the audio. So
it's a script and
then they'll use the
AI. Others will just
write it. It doesn't
matter which one you
do. Just pick one
to get your first
draft done. And then
what you do is
you copy each point,
not the whole script,
and you put it
into point bot and
you say, give me
feedback on this. And
it's going to tell
you what's worked, what
doesn't, whether there's any
payoffs, whether there's no
payoffs. And then it's
going to write an
optimized version. You can
then take that and
put it back on
your script document and
then edit it. Please
do not just use
that. It's not going
to be the best
script in the world.
It still can be
confusing because if you
give it confusing stuff,
it's not going to
make it work amazing.
If you give it
a good script, it'll
make it better, but
it won't make a
total piece of crap
good. So then what
you do is you
take that and you
start to edit it
and you do this
on every single point
that you make. Now,
one thing you have
to be careful with
AI, it loves writing
in sentences like this.
So you see that?
So if you look
at your scripts and
every line looks like
this, it's not a
natural way to spink.
And this is what
AI will do. So
what you want to
do is you need
to keep your sentence
varied. Don't get overwhelmed
or too bogged down
with this, like going,
is my sentence the
perfect length? But before
you finish it, just
do one final check
to make sure there's
a And you can
do that just by
looking at your page
going, oh, okay, all
the sentences seem slightly
different lengths. Now, the
next thing you need
to keep in mind
in writing is we
were taught to write
really formally at school.
And we don't want
to do that. We
want to write like
we're chatting to a
friend, but also you
want to write to
a reading age of
10. But Ed, my
viewers are so smart.
This is going to
put them off. Well,
nobody's ever been put
off because you made
something so easy to
understand. What this means
is we want to
write in a way
nobody feels left out.
And that's how you
get views. So avoid
really long, complex words
that only you understand.
Beginners might not. If
you present one sentence
out loud, and the
words are very hard
to present, then it's
a sign that the
complexity is making this
hard to understand. All
right, so before you
go and write this,
what I've done is
I've roasted some of
my own scripts to
show you every single
thing we've been talking
about in action. People
often tell me these
are some of the
most useful videos they
watch. I'll go through
setups, payoffs, emotions, frameworks,
and I'll show you
what I did wrong
as well, because I
make mistakes and then
how I'd fix them
now. And then after
that,
start planning your next
video.